Leah: As well as barriers to seeking
a diagnosis, some children and young
people may be reluctant to have a
diagnosis or any medical intervention
because of a range of different concerns.
Let’s have a look at
some of those concerns.
Rhiannon: There can be stigma associated
with receiving a mental health diagnoses,
and although this is lessening, as
young people are more open to exploring
mental health issues, there are
still those that would discriminate.
Being labelled with a mental
health diagnosis, might impact on
how others, including family and
friends may interact with someone.
Leah: Parents of a child or young
person, may become overly cautious
around a mental health label.
This may unintentionally reinforce
the underlying problem, such
as not encouraging an anxious
child to try new things.
For some a diagnosis can put an
emphasis on the problem being a part
of the child or young person and
maybe less likely to take into account
other external factors such as the
family dynamic and peer interactions.
Rhiannon: Some diagnoses are more helpful
than others, diagnoses of depression
or obsessive-compulsive disorder [OCD]
can validate suffering, however some
individuals might be sceptical of any
diagnostic label placed on them, as
they may feel dismissed by others who
choose to use their diagnosis as a way
of explaining away their valid emotions.
More severe diagnoses, such
as schizophrenia or borderline
personality disorder, can be used
to damage the credibility of the
sufferer, silencing their voice.
Leah: Some families of children and
young people, may fear that a diagnosis
will impact on their progression or
opportunities, such as not being able
to handle University or not being
able to have that job role they want,
due to their mental health issues.
This could then impact their
ambition for their future.
They may fear that the information held
about their diagnoses, may be available
to others, including potential employers.
They may wish to keep parts of their
life, or their mental health issues
private, however this is not the
case due to data protection laws.
Rhiannon: They may be concerned about
being put into a box, based solely on
their symptoms, rather than looking at
the cause of the symptoms themselves.
Sometimes it is an experience of trauma,
abuse, or neglect that brings on the
symptoms of mental health conditions.
They may not wish to address
these issues and feel that medical
intervention, may cause things that
have been suppressed to resurface.
Leah: How a diagnosis is received
is also mediated by the individual’s
life experiences and culture.
If the diagnosis is placed upon the
patient with no space for the individual’s
thoughts, queries, or concerns, then
it is likely that the individual
will reject the diagnosis and rebel
against any potential treatment plans.